Guide to the Altagor Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Altagor papers
1930-2009
GEN MSS 1466
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
23.25
(33 boxes)
The Altagor Papers, which span from 1930-2009, contain correspondence, personal papers, writings, artwork, printed material, objects, records, audio tapes, and other papers by or relating to the artist Altagor, also known as Andre Vernier.
Altagor, 1915-1992
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 17-28 (audiotape reels): Restricted fragile material. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Didier Lecointre-Dominique Drouet on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2017.
Arrangement
Organized into thirteen series: I. Novels and Classical Poems, 1930-1960. II. Simonia, 1942-1964. III. Poetic Fragments, 1936-1961. IV. Symphonic Poems and Odes, 1939-1948. V. Metapoesie and Metapoesie Lettrism, 1941-2001. VI. Discours Absolu, 1937-1958, VII. Recordings and Scores, 1943-2009. VIII. Notes, Notebooks, and Uncollected Texts, 1950-1984. IX. Writings, Theories, and Ideas, 1945-2002. X. Drawings and Paintings, 1957-1985. XI. Personal Papers and Photographs, undated. XII. Annotated Books, 1937-1986. XIII. Objects, 1976, undated.
Altagor
Altagor, also known as André Vernier (1915-1992), was a novelist, sound poet, and composer, who was often associated with the Lettrism movement. Born in the French province of Lorraine, he worked briefly as a coal miner before turning his hand to writing, musical composition, and art. From the 1930's until the end of his life, Altagor made objects and musical instruments, drew and painted, made audio recordings of his musical performances, and wrote in a variety of disciplines including poetry.
Scope and Contents
The Altagor Papers, which span from 1930-2009, contain correspondence, personal papers, writings, artwork, printed material, objects, long-playing records, audio tapes, and other papers by or relating to the artist Altagor, also known as Andre Vernier. These materials document Altagor's writings including drafts of his novels, manifestoes, typewriter poems, symphonic poems, and his most well-known works, "Discours absolu" and "Simonia."
This collection also contains Altagor's musical creations including his post-war compositions and scores, as well as designs for his musical instruments and the proto-type of one of them, the "pantaphone." Notebooks, correspondence, and reel-to-reel tapes document his performances, his creative practice, and his involvement with Lettrism.
Artists -- France; Composers -- France; French poetry -- 20th Century; Lettrism; Poets, French; Drawings (visual works); Musical instruments; Paintings (visual works); Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; Artists -- France -- 20th Century; Composers -- France -- 20th Century; Poets -- France -- 20th Century; Altagor, 1915-1992
- Novels and classical poems, 1930-1960; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Material within this series maintains the original organization found at time of acquisition.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains writings (primarily poetry), notes, artwork, and ephemera.
  - L'auberge de la Croix-du-Pape, undated (Box 1)
  - Poems, 1930-1960; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Extraits de poemes, 1937-1942 (Box 1)
  - Poesies classiques, undated (Box 1)
  - Le dieu chantant poeme, undated (Box 1)
  - Septuor a Y. M., 1942 (Box 1)
  - Sylvir, undated (Box 1)
  - Natais, 1953 (Box 1)
  - L'or du ciel tinte, undated (Box 1)
  - Nijinski perdu, undated (Box 1)
- Simonia, 1942-1964; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains writings, notes, artwork, and ephemera related to Altagor's epic poem "Simonia."
  - Ici Altagor "Un soir du tempete", 1942 (Box 2)
  - Simonia 601, 602, 603, 1943 (Box 2)
  - A Simonia 6 Sept 1945 (Box 2)
  - Simonia 116, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Simonia "Je marchais..", 1950 (Box 2)
  - Simonia--Ici s'acheve l'occident, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Simonia suite, 1947-1953 (Box 2)
  - Simonia "Un bonheur solitaire", 1953 (Box 2)
  - Fragment du chant perpetuel, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Tres court fragments de Simonia..."Je marche dans la ville", 1963 (Box 2)
  - Dedicace a Simonia l'imaginaire--"J'etais sur un pont...", 1964 (Box 2)
  - Zeda la cynique, circa 1957 (Box 2)
  - Extrait du chant perpetuel, circa 1942-1963 (Box 2)
  - Extrait de Simonia IV: Prelude au Discours Absolu, undated (Box 2)
  - Simonia VII fragments and final, undated (Box 2)
  - Simonia suite VIII, undated (Box 2)
  - Simonia VIII, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Drawings of Simonia, undated (Box 2)
  - Initiateurs, 1956 (Box 2)
- Poetic fragments, 1936-1961; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains writings (primarily typewritten and annotated poems), notes, and ephemera.
  - Fragments poétiques, 1936-1961; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Symphonic poems and odes, 1939-1948; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Symphonic poems, 1939-1945; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Corriga lumiège, circa 1940 (Box 3)
  - Symphonist odes, 1947-1948; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Métapoésie and metapoesie lettrism, 1941-2001; Series V; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  - Altagor I, undated (Box 3)
  - Phonetique lyrique universelle, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Considerations sur un metapoesie, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Altagor II, undated (Box 3)
  - Kalaande Iroue Cigor, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Metapoetics extracts, circa 1948-1952 (Box 3)
  - Grammes, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Neros Alcande, circa 1943-1950; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Altagor a Rhexenor, circa 1945 (Box 4)
  - Texts and images related to metapoesie, circa 1941-1963; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Metapoetics poems, undated (Box 4)
  - Metapoetics against Lettrism, circa 2001 (Box 5)
- Discours Absolu, 1937-1958; Series VI; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains writings, notes, artwork, and ephemera related to Altagor's work "Discours Absolu."
  - Arguments pour un discours absolu. N.R.F. Gallimard, undated (Box 5)
  - Idem--2 versions légèrement différentes, undated (Box 5)
  - Rectifications [suite], undated (Box 5)
  - Textes pour la préparation de l'édition de "Arguments pour un discours absolu", circa 1937-1958 (Box 5)
  - Arguments pour un discours absolu [N.R.F. Gallimard] Raye, undated (Box 5)
- Scores and recordings, 1943-2009; Series VII; 8.92; 13 boxes
  Organized into two subseries: Scores and Recordings.
  - Scores, 1943-1978; 0.42; (1 box)
    Contains scores, flyers, and ephemera related to Altagor's musical compositions and performances.
    - Radio Lorraine, 1947-1951; (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Variations perpetuelles, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Observation relatives, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Metapoesie presentation, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Ici Altagor, 1952-1955 (Box 5)
    - Conference/recital poesie ode symphoniste metapoesie, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Extrait du discours absolu, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Audition--arrangements symphoniques, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Ici Altagor, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Concert flyers, 1957-1964
    - ORTF documentation, 1968-1973 (Box 5)
    - Discours absolu--enregistrement du samedi 26 janvier 1957 Maguy (Box 5)
    - Manifeste Omega, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Musical instrument notes and designs, 1963-1978 (Box 5)
    - Un discours absolu partition, 1945 (Box 5)
    - Altagor--edition reduite, undated (Box 5)
    - Extraits des partitions synoptiques, 1945 (Box 5)
    - Altagor II, undated (Box 5)
    - Fragments voir 100 pages, 1957-1964 (Box 5)
    - Rhenenor!, 1950-1952 (Box 5)
    - Et maintenant ? j'oppose à l'inexpiabilité du monde..., 1943 (Box 5)
    - Anciennes partitions annules II, undated (Box 5)
    - Partitions auterieurs au discours absolu, 1957-1964 (Box 5)
  - Recordings, 1953-2009; 8.5; (12 boxes)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Boxes 17-27 (audiotape reels) and Box 28 (record albums): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    Contains analog media including audio recordings of poetry readings and musical performances by Altagor and others.
    - Audio recordings, circa 1953-1973; 3 (Box 17)
    - Baobab 9--métapoésie, 1981; 1 (Box 18)
    - Repiquages divers, circa 1977-1980; 1 (Box 18)
    - Audio recordings, undated; 3 (Box 18)
    - Divers: Frediva et Le Dynoméga ou Omégiste, circa 1977-1980; 1 (Box 18)
    - Hommage à Altagor., 2009; 1 (Box 18)
    - Altagor Métapoésie 1948/1965, 2002; 1 (Box 18)
    - Altagor--L'auteur du Discours Absolu, le grand dissident occulté de l'avant-garde des années 50, 2000; 1 (Box 18)
    - Métaphone + Métapoesié (1 of 3), circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:41:13; Program is distorted at times. The volume is low until about 22:00. (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104615829)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Métapoesié (2 of 3), 1953-1973; 1; 01:07:56; Static is heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104615837)
    - Métaphone + Métapoesié (3 of 3), 1953-1973; 1; 01:23:00; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104615845)
    - Dialogue Elise, Mad Dorseau, Altagor, Barbara Cassin, P. Benoit, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:47:47; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104615852)
    - Repiquages divers, 1970?; 1; 01:00:46; The program is distorted at times. A high amount of hum can be heard at about 30:24. The program ends abruptly. (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104615860)
    - Altagor repiques microsaude I, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:48:56 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104616025)
    - Audio recordings, circa 1953-1973; 5 (Box 20)
    - Audio recordings, circa 1953-1973; 6 (Box 21)
    - II, Superpositions, métaphone, plectophone and pantophone, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:23:58 (Box 22, Item barcode 39002104615878)
    - Nanifesles et discours absolu, circa 1953-1973; 1; 01:01:14; The program ends abruptly. (Box 22, Item barcode 39002104615886)
    - I Robert Wed; métaphone + plectophone, 1970-1971; 1; 00:49:51; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. The volume fluctuates throughout the program. (Box 22, Item barcode 39002104615894)
    - Vin[?] Sch[?], circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:14:53; The program begins abruptly. (Box 22, Item barcode 39002104615902)
    - Mulags I verso grecque, circa 1953-1973; 1; 01:46:50; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 22, Item barcode 39002104615910)
    - Le Soliste Altagor variations, 2000; 1; 02:07:02; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 22, Item barcode 39002104615928)
    - Audio recordings, circa 1953-1973; 7 (Box 23)
    - Divers Melaphonique, circa 1953-1973; 1; 01:04:30; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002104615936)
    - souie arec Barbara Cassin; métaphone, variations a la Paganini, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:31:58; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002104615944)
    - Altagor, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:20:11; Static can be heard on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002104615951)
    - Métapoésie (1948), circa 1953-1973; 1; 01:41:06; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002104615969)
    - III métaphone, dynamique + pantophone, primitif, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:23:15; Static can be heard on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002104615977)
    - métaphone perpétuel, Berretty, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:27:43; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002104615985)
    - Audio recordings, circa 1953-1973; 6 (Box 25)
    - Audio recordings, circa 1953-193; 5 (Box 26)
    - Altagor (1 of 2), circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:03:11 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104615993)
    - Altagor (2 of 2), circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:00:56 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002093778810)
    - Untitled, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:30:20; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104616009)
    - Altagor, circa 1953-1973; 1; 02:19:05 (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104616017)
    - Métaphone, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:26:40; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104616033)
    - métaphone, circa 1953-1973; 1; 00:42:02; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104616041)
    - solo de métaphone [Berretty]...fragments de E....; parole ri - pantophone (dynamique) ..., 1970 August; 1; 01:14:18; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104616058)
    - Pantophone + plectrophone; Colette...pantophone - métaphone..., 1973 November 8; 1; 01:02:32; Static can be heard on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104616066)
    - Vieille bande ancienne, 1963; 1; 00:22:47; The program is recorded at a low level for the first 11 minutes. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002104616074)
    - Dix Ans d'Essais Radiophoniques Du Studio Au Club D'Essai: 1942-1952, 1989; 5 (Box 28 (Record album storage))
- Notes and notebooks, 1950-1984; Series VIII; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Contains writings, notes, artwork, and ephemera related to Altagor's creative projects.
  - L'expression finale est musique absolue, 1965-1970 (Box 6)
  - A la recherche de mutants, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Altagor II, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Morgana ou l'anti-futur, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Altagor II--combinaisons polyphoniques et symphoniques, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Altagor transformel, circa 1977-1984 (Box 6)
  - Altagor II: Ici Altagor, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Ici Altagor, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Altagor poète musicien, peintre..." + B.E. [fin], circa 1977-1984 (Box 6)
  - A la recherche des mutants, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Altagor transformel, 1977-1984 (Box 6)
  - A la recherche des mutants 1966, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  - Mephisto, undated (Box 7)
  - Notebook, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Altagor extra monde, 1961-1962 (Box 7)
  - Notebook, 1961-1962 (Box 7)
  - Altagor au rythme de l'instantanée, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Anergor--Zeda la cynique, 1975-1980 (Box 7)
  - Altagor au rythme de l'instantanée, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Agenda/daybook, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Simonia Vi, VII, 1961-1962 (Box 8)
  - Altagor final variations sans fin, 1965-1970 (Box 8)
  - Metapoesie, 1950-1952 (Box 8)
  - Agenda/daybook, 1959 (Box 8)
  - Altagor au rythme de l'instantanée, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Partial manuscripts, undated (Box 8)
  - Altagor Extra-monde, 1961-1962 (Box 8)
  - Altagor II, 1961-1962 (Box 8)
  - Event posters, 2005, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
- Writings, theories, and ideas, 1945-2002; Series IX; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  - Ici Altagor, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Self-promotion documentation, 1945-1964 (Box 8)
  - Clippings and flyers, 1959-2002 (Box 8)
  - Du symbole à l'absolu, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Ici Altagor, circa 1950s-1960s; (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Invariants, undated (Box 9)
  - Untitled #304-#682, undated (Box 9)
  - Untitled (transformel), undated (Box 9)
  - Untitled (L'art absolu...), undated (Box 9)
  - Arguments, undated; (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Manifestos, circa 1950's (Box 9)
  - Resumes, undated (Box 9)
  - Notes, undated (Box 9)
  - Demonstrations, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Synoptics, undated (Box 9)
  - L'absolu, undated (Box 9)
  - Transformative speech, circa 1949 (Box 9)
  - Documents, 1970-1986 (Box 9)
  - Untitled (Salut pour Giordano Bruno...), undated (Box 10)
  - "Démonstration provisoire" automatic paintings, 1957-1964 (Box 10)
  - Untitled, numbered writings, undated (Box 10)
  - Extracts of text from flyers
  - Résumé des formes finales d'expression, undated (Box 31)
  - Primat de l'Absolu., undated (Box 31)
  - Photo collage, undated (Box 31)
- Drawings and paintings, 1957-1985; Series X; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Contains artwork, along with notes and ephemera related to Altagor's artistic endeavors.
  - Generation de figures, undated (Box 10)
  - Busta sorpresa #2, 1985 (Box 10)
  - Notebooks containing drawings and paintings, 1957-1964 (Box 10)
  - Drawings and paintings, 1957-1983; (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Drawings and paintings, 1957-1983; (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - Peinture-pulsion No. 1, 1971 (Box 12)
  - Portraits, 1962 (Box 12)
  - Altagor par Van de Ghys, 1960-1970 (Box 12)
  - Dynomographie lineaire, 1963 (Box 12)
  - Isomorphic paintings, undated (Box 12)
  - Drawings and paintings, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
- Personal papers and photographs, undated; Series XI; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains photographs, notes, artwork, and ephemera related to Altagor's life and work.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 12)
  - Pressbook, undated (Box 12)
- Annotated books, 1937-1986; Series XII; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Material within this series maintains the original organization found at time of acquisition, which is roughly alphabetical by author.
  Contains books annotated, both with writing and drawing, by Altagor.
  - Art Abstrait-Espace et mouvement, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Dictionnaire de la poésie française contemporaine, 1968 (Box 13)
  - Fac-similés de Daniel Jacomet catalogue, undated (Box 13)
  - Bloy, Leon--La Pal pamphlet 1885, 1979 (Box 13)
  - Bonnefoy, Claude--La poésie française, 1975 (Box 13)
  - Boulez, Pierre--Penser la musique aujourd'hui, 1964 (Box 13)
  - Breton, André--Nadja, 1976 (Box 14)
  - Brindeau, Serge--La poésie contemporaine de la langue française, 1973 (Box 14)
  - Casanova, Gaston--L'algèbre de Boole, 1968 (Box 14)
  - Comte--Catéchisme positiviste, 1966 (Box 14)
  - Cresson, André--La philosophie française, 1951 (Box 14)
  - Delay, Jean--La psychologie humaine, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Deslandes, André --Audiberti, 1964 (Box 15)
  - Ducassé, Pierre--Les grandes philosophies, 1954 (Box 15)
  - Estival, Robert--L'idéographie synthétique, 1960 (Box 15)
  - Faivre, Michèle--A cri ouvert, 1972 (Box 15)
  - Fichte--La destination de l'homme, 1942 (Box 15)
  - Guilleminault & Mahé--L'épopée de la révolte, 1963 (Box 15)
  - Le Corbusier--Quand les cathédrales étaient blanches, 1937 (Box 15)
  - Sabatier, Robert--Histoire de la poésie française, la poésie du vingtième siècle, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Soupault--Lautréamont Poésie 46., undated (Box 16)
  - Shakespeare, WIlliam--Richard III, Roméo et Juliette, 1964 (Box 16)
  - Schopenhauer--Le vouloir vivre l'art et la sagesse, 1983 (Box 16)
  - Solomon--Les mathématiques, 1970 (Box 16)
  - Dérivation, 1983 (Box 16)
  - La nouvelle mathématique, 1976 (Box 16)
- Objects, 1976, undated; Series XIII; 2.58; (2 boxes)
  Contains objects created by Altagor.
  - Rubber stamps, undated (Box 29)
  - Double Dames boardgame, 1976 (Box 30)
  - Pantophone, undated (Box 33 (Oversize))